Hello!
In today's episode of Bug Bounty Reports Explained
I will show how it was possible to send a
malicious GIF image in WhatsApp that could
take control over whole Android smartphone.
The video is based on an article by a guy
named Awakened.
Link, as always is in the description.
Low-level bug is something new on my channel
and I hope you will enjoy that!
Let's start with a GIF file.
It contains multiple images and when those
frames are being shown one after another,
they create an animation.
Usually, during such animation, frames have
the same size.
However, this is not enforced by GIF specification.
Frames can have different sizes, including
frames of size 0.
This is the structure used to store information
about GIFs from native Android library.
Most important for us is the rasterBits buffer.
It's where decoded frames are being stored.
In a typical GIF where all frames have the
same size, this buffer is just reused.
However, when width or height of a new frame
is greater than the previous one, the buffer
must be reallocated.
Reallocation is a combination of free and
malloc functions.
Malloc is a function used to allocate space.
You need to use it when you create a new variable
or an object.
Free is the function used to free the memory
after it's no longer needed so that it can
be assigned to another variable.
And coming back to our GIFs, the amount of
space to reallocate is just the size of the
new frame.
So if a GIF would have frames of sizes 4x4,
3x3 and 5x5, then after the first frame, there's
no need for reallocation, but after the second
frame the buffer would be reallocated with
25 bytes of space.
But what would happen if a new frame would
have size 5x0?
For the library it was enough if a new width
or new height was greater than the one in
the previous frame.
So with frame 5x0, the reallocation would
happen.
But the malloc would try to reallocate 5*0=0
bytes, so it would simply do nothing and the
reallocation would only free the memory.
So if we would have frames of sizes 4x4, 5x0,
5x0, info->rasterBits would be freed after
the first AND after the second frame.
And this is the double-free vulnerability.
But the question is - why is that actually
a problem?
It's the problem because in Android it leads
to 2 subsequent memory allocations returning
the same address.
Size of those two reallocations must be the
same as the size of double-freed buffer.
So when the first frame was 16 bytes and it
was double-freed, then the next 2 memory allocations
of size 16 will return the same address.
Now let's see how this worked in WhatsApp.
When you opened preview of files from WhatsApp
application, GIFs were parsed twice.
Let's create a malicious GIF that will trigger
the double-free vulnerability.
It contains 4 frames and their sizes are:
168, 0 bytes, 0 bytes and the size of the
4th frame doesn't really matter.
It's just there so the GIF is valid.
Before parsing frames, GifInfo object is allocated
with 168 bytes.
This number is not dependent from the size
of the first frame.
It's just that the GifInfo struct has 21 properties,
8 bytes each.
And we chose the size of the first frame to
match this number and not the other way around.
You'll see later why we needed that.
Now it's time to parse the frames.
First, rasterBits buffer is allocated 168
bytes for the first frame.
Then, it's freed twice, while parsing frames
2 and 3.
Parsing frame 4 does not cause any problems.
So now, after this buffer was double freed,
next 2 allocations of size 168 will return
the same address.
Let's now see what happens during the second
parse.
Again, 168 bytes are allocated for a new GifInfo
object.
Then, the first frame is being parsed and
again, 168 bytes are allocated for it.
So this is the moment, when malloc returns
the same address again.
So now both info and info->rasterBits are
pointing to the same address.
So such GIF causes WhatsApp to crash.
But it wasn't our goal, our goal was to execute
arbitrary commands.
Let's now take a look how this could be achieved.
Soon after parsing each frame, info->rewindFunction
was called.
Since info object has the same size and address
as our first frame, the program now thinks
that our first frame is the info object so
we have complete control over it.
And the program remembers where the rewindFunction
was.
So now, we can prepare our first frame so
that when the program wants to execute that
function, it executes whatever we want.
And what do we want?
We want a reverse shell.
Now stay calm people, because it's time for
some assembly.
To reach our goal, we need to set proper values
to PC and X0 registers.
Registers in assembly are like special variables
that contain specific information.
PC (program counter) stores the address of
the next instruction.
So we will want the address of the system
function there.
And the get it there, we need to replace the
address of the rewindFunction.
And X0 register stores the first function
argument, so we want to put our reverse shell
command in there.
So now, the researcher had to find a function
that will set the X0 register to what he wanted
and then jump to the system function.
And this is the gadget that he found.
I will explain it while at the same time creating
the first frame of the GIF, which will at
the same time be a GifInfo object.
The idea is that from rewindFunction we jump
to this gadget, it sets a proper X0 register
and the we go to the system function, reaching
our goal.
Originally, rewindFunction was at offset 0x80
of the info object.
So this is the place where we put the address
of this gadget.
Then, ldr instruction from this gadget loads
the value from register X19 with offset 0x18
to register X8.
X8 will be the address where we jump next.
It's what blr instruction at the end does.
And X19 is our first frame.
So at offset 0x18 we put the address of the
system function.
The second instruction loads the value form
our first frame with offset 0x20 to register
X0 which will our argument.
So in our frame, at this offset we put our
command with reverse shell.
And that's pretty much the whole exploit.
The problem is that we need to get the addresses
of our gadget and the system function.
And there are 2 practical attack scenarios
for this.
One of them is that a malicious application,
installed on the victim's phone gets those
addresses easily, because they are native
libraries and the addresses only change while
the phone is rebooted.
Then, this application would create a malicious
GIF, save on victim's phone and once the victim
opened a preview in WhatsApp, the exploit
would get triggered.
The other attack scenario is that the attacker
gets those addresses using information disclosure
vulnerability and then the attacker prepares
the GIF, sends to the victim and once the
victim opens the preview in WhatsApp, in gets
triggered.
You can generate your own malicious GIF using
the repo that's linked in the description
but of course, the vulnerability has been
patched and latest versions of WhatsApp are
no longer exploitable.
The vulnerability affected WhatsApp but it
was actually a bug in native Android library
so I don't think the researcher got any bounty
for it, because WhatsApp security team just
forwarded the report to library maintainers.
Lately, both on YouTube and on Twitter I did
a poll, asking you what you would like to
see more on my channel and low-level bugs
were highly rated, so I hope you like this
video.
But if you have any other suggestions, feel
free to comment them down below.
If you have learnt something new today, leave
a like and leave a subscription.
Thanks for watching and goodbye!